Guide to the Carnegie Endowment for International Peace pamphlet and microfilm collection, 1817-1950 MS2110
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
- Bound manuscripts, MS2110 Series 4; no content
  - A Preliminary Draft of A Survey of the Study of International Relations in the United States: Mimeographed Proof, Prepared in Connection with the Program of Research in International Relations of the Social Science Research Council Under the Direction of James T. Shotwell, 06/1933 (Box 58, Folder 4)
    Bound in brown paper covers. Ms. note on cover giving published title. Ms. note on title page mentions letter from Shotwell about published version. Stamp of Carnegie Endowment for International Peace Library on cover. Confidential proof for members of the Committee on Problems and Policy of the Social Science Research Council and of the American National Committee on Internatinal Cooperation. Collaborators include: George A. Finch, Edith E. Ware, A. Curtis Wilgus, Edward R. Murrow, Heber Harper, Alice Cheyney, Carol Riegelman. Edited by Grover Clark. Formerly call number: Ind. Ms. Bd. 37
  - Copy of Report dated March 28, 1919, made to the Acting Director of the Division of Intercourse and Education: typescript, by Christian L. Lange, Special Corespondent of the Division at Christiana, Norway, 03/28/1919 --05/19/1919 (Box 58, Folder 5)
    Report concerns postwar conditions in England, Belgium, and Holland; the work of the Inter-parliamentary Union; and the formation of the League of Nations. Norwegian Nobel Peace Prize laureate, 1921; secretary-general, Inter-parliamentary Union, 1909-1933; member, Norwegian delegation to League of Nations, 1920-1938. Report concerns postwar conditions in England, Belgium, and Holland; the work of the Inter-parliamentary Union; and the formation of the League of Nations. Provenance: At head of title: For the trustees of the Carnegie Endowment only. Strictly confidential. "Copy for Dr. James Brown Scott, May 19, 1919." Stamp of Carnegie Endowment for International Peace Library on title page. Formerly call number: Ind. Ms. Bd. 38
  - L'Arbitrage de la Chambre de Commerce Internationale: typescript, 03/13/1934 (Box 58, Folder 6)
    Technical advisor to the Court of Arbitration of the International Chamber of Commerce. Explains the work of the Court of Arbitration of the International Chamber of Commerce. Formerly call number: Ind. Ms. Bd. 39
  - The Brazilian-Bolivian Arbitral Tribunal, 1910 (Box 58, Folder 7)
    Formerly call number: Ind. Ms. Bd. 40. Translation of published version: O tribunal arbitral brasilerio-boliviano. Rio de Janeiro: Imprensa nacional, 1910. Apparently made for the use of Carnegie Endowment for International Peace staff. "The purpose of this book is to show in summarization, the origin and course of the Brazilian-Bolivian Arbitration Tribunal." Formerly Ind. Ms. Bd. 40.
  - Russian S.F.S.R., Treaty of Peace Between Russia and Estonia, [London, H.J. Ryman, ltd., Printers, 1920 ca. (Box 59, Folder 1, Item 1)
    Signed in the town of Tartu, February 2, 1920. Ratified by the Constituent assembly of Esthonia on February 13, and by the Council of commissaries of the people of the Soviet republic of Russia on February 4. The ratification was notified on February 14, 1920, and the exchange of ratification took place at Moscow on March 30, 1920. Formerly call number: Ind. Ms. Bd. 41
  - Russian S.F.S.R., Treaty of Peace Between Russia and Estonia: Manuscript, [London, H.J. Ryman, ltd., Printers, 1920 ca. (Box 59, Folder 1, Item 2)
    Stamp of Carnegie Endowment for International Peace Library on p. 1. With: published version. Appears to be an early draft of the treaty, differing slightly in wording from final version. Treaty was signed in Tartu, Estonia, on Feb. 2, 1920. Formerly call number: Ind. Ms. Bd. 41
  - Decision of the second group of the Supreme Court in amparo no. 697/38, docket 2902/39/2a: Brought by the Compania Mexicana de Petroleo " El Aguila" et al., Against the Expropriation Law ...: typescript, (mechanically reproduced) Mexico, Suprema Corte de Justicia., 1939 (Box 59, Folder 2)
    Stamp of Carnegie Endowment for International Peace Library on cover; pencil notations throughout. With: English version of the law of expropriation (3 leaves). English translation of the decision. The court decided against the Compan~i´a Mexicana and other oil companies on most points. Formerly call number: Ind. Ms. Bd. 42f
  - Paris Peace Conference, Commission on Prisoners of War, Reports, 1919 (Box 59, Folder 3)
    Chiefly typescript (mechanically reproduced) (with some printed material) reports, in English and French, concerning the repatriation of German, Austrian, and Bulgarian prisoners of war. Formerly call number: Ind. Ms. Bd. 43f
  - United States, American Commission to Negotiate Peace, Minutes, 07/08/1919 --07/16/1919 (Box 59, Folder 4)
    From the Carnegie Endowment for International Peace Library. Copy of James Brown Scott. The American Commission to Negotiate Peace was the U.S. Delagation to the Paris Peace Conference (1919-1920). Minutes (mechanically reproduced typescripts) of July 8 and July 16, 1919 meetings of the commissioners and the technical experts of the American Commission to Negotiate Peace. Formerly call number: Ind. Ms. Bd. 44f
  - Great Britain, Delegation to the Paris Peace Conference, Memoranda, 03/26/1919 --11/26/1919 (Box 59, Folder 5)
    Chiefly memoranda and letters (chiefly typescript mechanically reproduced), in French and English, concerning various portions of the treaty with Germany, including disposition of the German merchant marine. Formerly call number: Ind. Ms. Bd. 45f
  - Paris Peace Conference (1919-1920), Drafting Committee, Papers, 05/1919 --11/1919 (Box 59, Folder 6)
    Chiefly typescript, with some printed and ms. material, in French, English and Italian, concerning sections of the peace treaties, chiefly those with Germany and Austria. Includes handwritten notes by James Brown Scott. Formerly call number: Ind. Ms. Bd. 46f
  - United States, American Commission to Negotitate Peace, Minutes, 07/01/1919 --09/04/1919 (Box 59, Folder 7)
    The American Commission to Negotiate Peace was the U.S. Delegation to the Paris Peace Conference (1919-1920.) Minutes (typescripts carbon copies and typescripts mechanically reproduced) of meetings of a steering committee that was apparently formed July 1, 1919. James Brown Scott was elected chairman, and Allen W. Dulles was secretary. Concerns chiefly treaties with Austria, Bulgaria, and Hungary. Formerly call number: Ind. Ms. Bd. 47f
  - Die Versammlung der Volker des Erdkreises: die Letzte Szene der Gottlichen Komodie: die Idioten, typescript, 1932 (Box 59, Folder 8)
    Satirical play about world government. Formerly call number: Ind. Ms. Bd. 48f
  - Die Idiotenanstalt der Vereinigten Staaten von Europa, typescript, 1932 (Box 60, Folder 1)
    Satirical prose and poetry concerning world government. Du¨sseldorf 1932. Als Manuscript gedruckt. Formerly call number: Ind. Ms. Bd. 49f
  - Record and decision: James Pugh vs. Panama under convention of October 15, 1932: typescript, 1931-1933 Records and Decisions, 1930-1934 (Box 60, Folder 2)
    Lutz was an American international lawyer whose home was in Washington, D.C. Summary: Copies of documents that Lutz collected to write a legal article about a case, which concerned the British government's attempt to recover restitution for the death of James Pugh, an Irish seaman, at the hands of Panamanian police officers. Judge James J. Lenihan, the arbitrator, decided against the claim. Formerly call number: Ind. Ms. Bd. 61
  - Comments of the German delegation on report of Commission on Responsibility for the War, 05/28/1919 (Box 61, Folder 1)
    Typescript of translation from German. German delegation to the Paris Peace Conference (1919-1920) replies to the report on the responsibility for World War I. Includes 21-leaf report by Hans Delbru¨ck, Albrecht Mendelssohn Bartholdy, Count Montegelas, and Max Feber. Formerly Ind. Ms. Bd. f 32
  - Education for peace in the daily vacation Bible schools of New York City, 1935 (Box 61, Folder 2)
    Imogene McPherson was superintendent in charge of the Metropolitan Federation of Daily Vacation Bible Schools in New York City. Account of experiment in peace education in the daily vacation Bible schools of New York City, 1935. Formerly Ind. Ms. Bd. 34.
- James B. Scott materials, MS2110 Series 5; no content
  This series contains miscellaneous material from James B. Scott. This material has not yet been processed. See staff for assistance.
  - "From 'De Toekomstige Vrede" v.3, 10/31/1918 (Box 50, Folder 1)
  - "Attitude of Germany toward arbitration", 05/16/1917 (Box 50, Folder 2)
  - Photograph of the League of Nations library, 1929 (Box 50, Folder 3)
  - Assorted Carnegie peace pamphlet material, 1918-1939 (Box 50, Folder 4)
  - Scott addresses contents, 1925-1933 (Box 50, Folder 5)
  - Remarks of Mr. James Brown Scott at the dinner of the Pan American conference on capital cities, Hotel Mayflower, Washington D.C., 04/27/1925 (Box 50, Folder 6)
  - Bibliography of the writings of James Brown Scott, 05/15/1928 (Box 50, Folder 7)
  - The War Lord, 02/13/1917 (Box 50, Folder 9)
  - The protection of racial and religious minorities, 1925 ca. (Box 50, Folder 10)
  - How to end war, 1931 ca. (Box 50, Folder 11)
  - The right honorable James, Viscount Bryce of Dechmont, 1922 ca. (Box 50, Folder 12)
    Authored by James B. Scott
  - Select list of references on the permanent court of international justice, 04/12/1923 (Box 50, Folder 13)
  - Permanent court of international justice, bibliography, 04/1923 (Box 50, Folder 14)
  - Select bibliographies No. 2, the American Institute of International Law and the codification of international law, 07/28/1933 (Box 50, Folder 15)
  - Select list of references of the permanent court of international justice, 07/24/1923 (Box 50, Folder 16)
  - Permanent court of international justice, supplement No. 1 to select list of references, 12/29/1924 (Box 50, Folder 17)
  - The 150th anniversary of Washington's general orders at Valley Forge, 05/06/1928 (Box 50, Folder 18)
  - An interview of its president, James Brown Scott, on leaving Cuba, 03/09/1929 (Box 50, Folder 19)
  - The treaty between Italy and the Vatican, 02/11/1929 (Box 50, Folder 20)
    Address of Mr. James Brown Scott before the American Society of International Law.
  - Address of Mr. James B. Scott, President of the Institut Francais de Washington, at the commemoration of the fifth centenary of the Chevauchee of Jean d' Arc, 05/04/1929 (Box 50, Folder 21)
  - Address of Mr. James B. Scott at the laying of the corner-stone of the palace of the American Institute of International Law, 05/19/1929 (Box 50, Folder 22)
  - Palavras Pronunciadas, 05/19/1929 (Box 50, Folder 23)
  - Remarques de James Brown Scott a la ceremonie de la pose de la premiere pierre du Palais de l'Institut Americain de Droit International, 05/19/1929 (Box 50, Folder 24)
  - La Decouverte de L'Amerique et son influence sur le droit international, 10/12/1929 (Box 50, Folder 25)
  - Remarks of James Brown Scott at the formal opening of the Academy of International Law of Havana Cuba, 10/30/1929 (Box 50, Folder 26)
  - Remarks of James Brown Scott at the banquet of the National Woman's Party, New Willard Hotel, Washington, D.C., 12/07/1929 (Box 50, Folder 27)
  - Remarks of Mr. James Brown Scott on the radio program of the National Student Federation of America, 01/03/1930 (Box 50, Folder 28)
  - Remarks on the nationality of children, 01/08/1930 (Box 50, Folder 29)
  - "The individual, the state, the international community," an address by James Brown Scott, 04/23/1930 (Box 50, Folder 30)
  - "For the best interests of the United States, is this so-called Roosevelt Doctrine either necessary or desireable," an address by James B. Scott, 08/11/1930 (Box 50, Folder 31)
  - Remarks of James Brown Scott on the presentation of his portrait to the law school of Harvard University, 10/28/1930 (Box 50, Folder 32)
  - Remarks of James Brown Scott, as presiding officer at a meeting of the Woodward Wilson Foundation, 01/04/1931 (Box 50, Folder 34)
  - "The international community," an address delivered by James Brown Scott, 01/04/1931 (Box 50, Folder 35)
  - "Something attempted-something done," address delivered by James Brown Scott, 06/20/1932 (Box 50, Folder 36)
  - Remarks at a luncheon in honor of the chairman and governing board of the Pan American Union, 04/12/1933 (Box 50, Folder 38)
  - "International law, municipal law and their sanctions," presidential address delivered before the opening session of the twenty-seventh annual meeting of the American Society fo International Law, 04/27/1933 (Box 50, Folder 39)